<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands warning by late frowning providences, especially the immediate hand of God upon the straits-fleet improved in a sermon preacht April 1st, 1694 ... : from Ezekiel V, viii ... / by Jonathan Owen ...</title>
            <author>Owen, Jonathan.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O826</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17899</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13164931</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13164931</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98219</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53745)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98219)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 431:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands warning by late frowning providences, especially the immediate hand of God upon the straits-fleet improved in a sermon preacht April 1st, 1694 ... : from Ezekiel V, viii ... / by Jonathan Owen ...</title>
                  <author>Owen, Jonathan.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by John Harris ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ezekiel V, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98219:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98219:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Englands Warning,</hi> By Late Frowning PROVIDENCES: ESPECIALLY THE Immediate Hand of GOD UPON THE STRAITS-FLEET. Improved in a SERMON, Preacht <hi>April</hi> 1ſt. 1694.</p>
            <p>Wherein is plainly ſhew'd the Cauſes and Tokens of Gods preſent Controverſie with us, eſpecially for our Non-improvement of National Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances to an Obliged Reformation.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>From <hi>EZEKIEL</hi> V. viii.</bibl>
               <p>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, behold, I, even I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, and will execute Judgments in the midſt of thee, in the ſight of the Nations.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luke 13.3.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Micah 6.9.</bibl>
               <p>The Lords Voice crieth unto the City, and the Man of Wiſdom ſhall ſee thy Name; hear ye the Rod, and who hath appointed it.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ezekiel 13.13.</bibl>
               <p>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, I will even rent it with a ſtormy Wind in my Fury; nnd there ſhall be an overflowing ſhower in mine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and great Hail-ſtones in my Fury to conſume it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Jonathan Owen</hi> Paſtor of a Congregation in <hi>Southwark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be Sold by <hi>John Harris</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98219:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98219:2"/>
            <head>TO Capt. Anthony Clifford, At <hi>Peckham</hi> near <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Subject I write upon I muſt confeſs looks with a diſmal Aſpect upon this ſinful Nation; and were not I well aſſured of your full Satisfaction in, and your Zealous Affection to the preſent mercifully Eſtabliſht Government, (even to the hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your Perſon as formerly, if not ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annuated) I ſhould not venture to ſhelter this poor Eſſay for the Publick Welfare under the Patronage of your Noble Name. Nor do I doubt but you lodge the like Charitable Thoughts in your Breaſt concerning your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Relate, who in Compliance with the Auditors of this plain Sermon, is at laſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with to expoſe this his mean Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to Publick View and Cenſure, as being conſtrained thereunto by them that judge bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:98219:3"/>of it than my ſelf, and to whom as I now ſtand related I can deny no reaſonable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt for the Publick's and their good: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hope, <hi>Sir,</hi> you will put an amicable conſtruction upon the whole, and condeſcend to admit this Attempt into your favourable acceptance, and alſo follow it with your fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Prayers; that the End propounded, <hi>viz.</hi> The Convincing and Awakening this ſinful ſecure Nation, that becauſe the Sins ſpecified therein abound in the midſt of us, and our late National Deliverances have not been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to a general Reformation, therefore God by his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Judgments, eſpecially his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Hand upon the <hi>Straits-Floet,</hi> doth evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently declare he hath a Controverſie with us. That this Neceſſary End might through in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluencing Grace be obtain'd, is and ſhall be in conjunction with yours, the hearty Prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Unworthy Nephew, <hi>Jonathan Owen.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98219:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Candid Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou haſt now in thy Hands a plain Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, not Poliſht with that Art and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence which many are ſtudious of, but with an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire to promote the Happineſs of this ſinful threatned Nation, which the immediate Hand of God upon the <hi>Straits-Fleet</hi> gave birth unto. I did once little think and in part determine with my ſelf, never to expoſe my weak Endeavours to Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick View and Cenſure; but ſince by a more than ordinary Hand of Divine Providence, attended with common difficulties from the unſtable, I am (with the Favour of the preſent Government) fixed in a Paſtoral Relation, over a Church of Chriſt, whoſe Souls to my utmoſt I would gladly ſerve, and for Chriſt and their ſakes, ſpend and be ſpent, and in the proſecution of this high and noble End; I would
<pb facs="tcp:98219:4"/>prudently take hold of every opportunity, whether ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or frowning, which preſents it ſelf; and becauſe ſome that ſat under my Miniſtry are engaged in this unhappy Fleet, both in a Military and Civil reſpect, and amongſt the great number of precious Souls, that with the greateſt horror, and moſt amazing out-cry ſhot the Gulf of Eternity, there is but one as we yet hear loſt and that not confirmd; the General concern of the Nation, with, this no ſmall Mercy, made ſuch an impreſſion upon me, as to put by my intended Subject, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd me upon this awful one, <hi>Ezek. 5.8.</hi> as that which I judged to be the loud Voice of Providence to us; concluding from hence that doubtleſs, God hath a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie with us; but not becauſe of the Happy Revolution of Publick Affairs, as unthinking Dreamers do falſly imagine, but becauſe our unſpeakable Mercy, in our late Deliverance, is not improved to an obliged Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; for it may too truly be ſaid of us, as <hi>Pſal. 106.7.</hi> We remembred not the Multitude of his Mercies, but provoked him at the Sea, even at the <hi>Red Sea;</hi> as for thoſe (to ſpeak mildly) if not Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> without yoak, yet Perſons of low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, if any, for Gods Glory, and the Publick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, that are longing to go back into <hi>Egypt,</hi> that evidently make their own Intereſt not the Publicks, the Idol of their Care and Endeavours; as for theſe I hope every Prudent Man will take heed and beware of
<pb facs="tcp:98219:4"/>them, (as Vipers in their Native Land) and in Praying for them, leave them to the Juſtice of the Nation; in the mean time let us improve our preſent Mercies, and bleſs God for what we enjoy of Peace and Liberty at home, and chearfully contribute to this neceſſary defenſive War abroad, ſince our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer himſelf is expoſed to the greateſt Dangers, (whom God Preſerve and Proſper.) Reader, if with the preſent Hand of God ſtretcht out againſt us, this Sermon might obtain its deſegned and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired end, then may we be a happy People, and I ſhall greatly rejoyce, who in compliance with ſome of them that affectionately heard it, for Subſtance as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory ſerves, have thrown in my ſmall Mite, for the general good of my Native Countrey, and ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it with my Prayers, who am thine in the bonds of the Goſpel,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Jonathan Owen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:98219:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98219:5"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>EZEKIEL V. viii.</bibl>
                  <p>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold, I, even I am againſt thee, and will execute Judgments in the midſt of thee, in the ſight of the Nations.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>THE Spirit of God ſets forth the Duty of Goſpel Miniſters, by the Name of <hi>Watchmen,</hi> Ezek. 3.17. <hi>Son of Man, I have made thee a Watchman unto the Houſe of Iſrael; therefore hear the Word at my Mouth, and give them warning from me:</hi> Who in faithfulneſs to whom they relate, muſt give ſeaſonable warning of all approaching Calamities and Dangers, that ſo there may be either a happy Prevention, or a becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Submiſſion to what is otherwiſe inevitably befalling them. Now that I might approve my ſelf to Chriſt, my Country, and thoſe I Watch over in the Lord, I ſhall endeavour to aſſiſt you in making a right Improvement of the late awakening Diſpenſations of God to us in theſe Kingdoms; eſpecially the immediate Hand of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Straits-Fleet:</hi> In Order to do this, I have exercis'd my Thoughts upon this awful Subject: <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God, I even I am againſt thee, and will execute Judgments in the midſt of thee, in the ſight of the Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this and the foregoing Verſe, the Prophet doth diſcharge the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a faithful Watchman; and not fearing to give them Diſturbance in their ſleepy ſecure State, he lets them underſtand what eminent Dangers their great Abominations had brought them into, for as much as now God did manifeſtly declare himſelf to be againſt them. In the preceding Verſe, I find the Prophet in the Name of God, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges them with their Wickedneſs thus, <hi>becauſe ye multiplyed more than the Nations that are round about you;</hi> ſome by this underſtand the <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98219:6"/>manifold Bleſſings and ſignal Favours which God gave them, and ſhould have been improved to thankfulneſs and Obedience to God; but were not: but I humbly conceive it rather relates to their Sins; <hi>becauſe ye multiplied more than the Nations that are round about you</hi> in Sin; thy Tranſgreſſions have been more and of a deeper Dye than theirs, thou haſt more grievouſly offended than the very Heathens that know not God; and the following Words explain it: <hi>And have not walked in my Statutes, neither have kept my Judgments, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have done according to the Judgments of the Nations that are round about you:</hi> i. e. The Heathens have been more ſaithful to their falſe Gods, than you have been to Me the only True God; they have by the Light of Nature been more ſtedfaſt to their cruel Injunctions, than you have been to my Holy and Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions; they have been ſtedfaſt to their Gods; but you have been given to change; and not only to comply with them, but you have exceeded them in Sin and Guilt: <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, I, even I,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the Words you have theſe things conſiderable:</p>
            <p n="1">1. An Argumentative, awful Preface, <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God;</hi> Wherefore? <hi>Becauſe ye multipti'd more than the Nations that are round about you:</hi> You excell'd them in Sin and Wickedneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You have a neceſſary Duty call'd for and required from them; <hi>Behold,</hi> the Word imports the Clearneſs, Certainty and Awful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the things he is about to Denounce and Declare, as being ſomewhat extraordinary, which duely weighed by them, might make their Ears Tingle to hear it, and cauſe their Hearts to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Meditate upon it; for it's the worſt and ſevereſt of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God, I, even I, am againſt thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You have the Subject matter it ſelf, which I can ſcarce with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Horror and Trepidation mention: <hi>I, even, I am againſt thee;</hi> mark the Congemmination, <hi>I, even I,</hi> not once <hi>I,</hi> but twice <hi>I; even I,</hi> that it might make the greater Impreſſion upon them. <hi>I</hi> that formerly ſet my Heart upon you, am now wean'd from you; <hi>I</hi> that choſe you before other Nations, not becauſe you were more than others, but only becauſe <hi>I</hi> had a Favour for you: <hi>I even I,</hi> that took you into ſpecial Covenant with my ſelf, do now declare againſt you; <hi>I</hi> that have Graciouſly ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intended you, do now take my Heart off from you; <hi>I</hi> that have wrought wonders for you in the ſight of the Nations, <hi>I</hi> that have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98219:6"/>preſerved you alive in Famine, <hi>I</hi> that deliver'd you out of the Hands of the Cruel Tyrant <hi>Pharaoh, I</hi> that divided the <hi>Red-Sea,</hi> that fed you in the Wilderneſs, <hi>I</hi> that have carried you as upon Eagles Wings all your days, <hi>I</hi> that have been a Father and a Friend to you, <hi>I, even I am againſt you,</hi> my Heart can't be toward you, nor can I bear with you any longer.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You have the plain Evidence and full Confirmation of this his being turn'd to be their Enemy, <hi>And will execute Judgments in the midſt of thee:</hi> I will not only ſhake the Rod over you, but I will lay it heavy upon you; and you ſhall ſmart and groan under it ſenſibly. What I will do in my fury, ſhall not be done in a Corner, or upon a part of you, but <hi>in the midſt of you:</hi> I will ſtrike at the very Heart, you ſhall feel it; for I will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute Judgments one upon another in the midſt of you; you ſhall be ſick of my Smiting, and groan under my heavy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the midſt of you; my Heart ſhall not Pity, my Hand ſhall not help you; but I will with my immediate Hand afflict you with Judgments one on the Neck of another in the midſt of you.</p>
            <p n="5">5. You have the fore Aggravation of it, and that <hi>in the ſight of the Nations round about;</hi> as your Sins have been, ſo ſhall your Sufferings be; you diſhonour'd me with your Abominations before the Heathens, and I will execute my Judgments before the Nations: You have not ceas'd to prophane my Name before them, and in their ſight will I vindicate my great Name; and ſhew that I am of <hi>Purer Eyes than to behold Iniquity;</hi> they that beheld your Sins, ſhall be Spectators of my Judgments in the midſt of you; <hi>Therefore thus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>From the Words, I ſhall Collect and Depoſe ſeveral Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, but ſhall ſpeak more fully to the laſt of them.</p>
            <p>Doct. 1. <hi>That Miniſters of the Goſpel, like faithful Watchmen, muſt give their People warning of apprehended, preſent and approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Judgments:</hi> So did the Prophet, and ſo muſt all others, if they will be faithful to Chriſt, and the precious Souls they are to watch over: We muſt declare, <hi>what of the Night,</hi> and like <hi>Paul, keep back nothing,</hi> that we might have their Record, that we are <hi>clear from the Blood of all men, Acts</hi> 20.27. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.1. There faith God to the Prophet, <hi>Cry aloud, ſpare not, lift up thy voice
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98219:7"/>like a Trumpet, and ſhew my People their Tranſgreſſions, and the Houſe of Jacob their Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doct. 2. <hi>That whatſoever Perſonal, Family or National Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments befall a People, it is certain that Sin is the meritorious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing cauſe of them:</hi> It's Sin that is the Teeming Mother of all Miſchief, the procuring cauſe of all Calamities whatſoever: Its that which lets in all Miſery, and cauſeth Deſtruction to come in upon a People like an armed Man, or an overflowing Flood; <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, &amp;c becauſe ye multipli'd more than,</hi> &amp;c. It was <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> Abominations, which inevitably brought their Deſolations; and it's <hi>Englands</hi> Sins that cauſe God to execute Judgments in the midſt of us at this day: If Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds without controul, Judgments will follow, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.23. for he doth <hi>nothing without a cauſe;</hi> and it's not difficult to relate what is the Cauſe of great Anger being gone out from the Lord againſt this Land; not the late Deliverance which God graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly wrought for us, as ſome little better than <hi>Papiſts</hi> dream, but our not improving ſo unſpeakable a Mercy to an obliged Reformation.</p>
            <p>Doct. 3. <hi>In all the Judgments, which are executed upon a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, God himſelf hath a Hand in it;</hi> and ſometimes more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly than at other times, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2.24, 25. <hi>Who gave Jacob for a ſpoil, and Iſrael to the Robbers; did not the Lord, he againſt whom we have ſinned? For they would not walk in his ways, neither were they obedient unto his Law. Therefore he hath poured upon him the Fury of his Anger, and the ſtrength of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, and it hath ſet him en fire round about, yet he knew not; and it burned him, yet he laid it not to Heart.</hi> No <hi>Afflictions</hi> or Judgments <hi>ariſe out of the Duſt;</hi> it's an Expreſſion more fit for an Atheiſt than Chriſtians, to attribute Afflictions and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to Chance and Fortune: <hi>J will execute Judgment in the midſt of thee, in the ſigbt of the Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doct. 4. <hi>When God for the Sins of a Nation doth execute Judgments, as he reaſonably expects, ſo they ſeriouſly ſhould take due notice of it:</hi> Therefore <hi>thus ſaith the Lord, behold,</hi> &amp;c. it's no ſmall Aggravation of our Guilt and Miſery, for Perſons lightly to paſs over the evident tokens of Gods diſpleaſure: This is but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98219:7"/>to intangle our ſelves ſo much the more, and to make our bands of Sorrow with the Judgments of God ſo much the ſtronger and heavier, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.11. <hi>When thy Hand is lifted up, they will not ſee, but they ſhall ſee and be aſhamed at it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doct. 5. <hi>Of all Judgments, for the great God to manifeſt or declare himſelf to be againſt a People or a Nation, is the worſt and ſoreſt.</hi> As <hi>David</hi> ſaid of <hi>Goliah</hi>'s Sword, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.9. <hi>There is none like that;</hi> ſo of all that can befall a People, there is none like this Judgment, for God to be againſt them, that have ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt him: <hi>I, even I, am againſt thee, and will execute Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the midſt of thee, in the ſight of the Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Proſecution of this Doctrine, I ſhall endeavour to keep to this Method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. I ſhall lay down ſome Propoſitions to explicate this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and to preſerve good thoughts of God, tho' in a way of Judgment with a ſinful People and Nation.</item>
               <item>II. I ſhall make ſome inquiry, What are thoſe Sins that have, and it is to be fear'd now do, provoke God to proceed in a way of Judgment againſt a People or a Nation.</item>
               <item>III. I ſhall demonſtrate, what are the diſmal Signs and ſad To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Gods being againſt a People or a Nation.</item>
               <item>IV. I ſhall evince, that of all Judgments which may befall a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or a Nation, there is none comparable to, or greater than Gods manifeſt declaring himſelf to be againſt a People or Nation.</item>
               <item>V. I ſhall Improve the whole with ſome Practical Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">(1.) The Propoſitions needful to explicate the Doctrine, they are theſe following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Prop.</hi> The Great, Soveraign and Alwiſe God, doth not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely delight in ſetting himſelf againſt a People, or in manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting himſelf to be againſt a Nation in a way of Judgment: God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98219:8"/>forbid that any ſhould have ſuch hard thoughts of a good and a gracious God, as to imagine that he takes delight in waſting and deſtroying his Creatures! he hath fully declar'd himſelf to the contrary in his Word, which we have the higheſt Reaſon to believe: For he is Truth, and can't deny himſelf: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church kept up believing good thoughts of God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hotteſt Furnace of Affliction: <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.32, 33. <hi>Tho he cauſe grief, yet will he have Compaſſion, according to the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his Mercies; for he doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the Children in of Men:</hi> i. e, He doth not <hi>afflict from his Heart,</hi> but like a tender Loving Father, who will not ſpare to correct his Child as the Fault requires, but yet not without natural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy and Bowels: Thence it is, that Judgment, tho' it be his Work, yet it is calld <hi>his ſtrange Act, Iſa.</hi> 28.21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.4. <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is not in me,</hi> i. e. againſt my People. Well, let it remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber'd, that God doth not abſolutely delight to be executing his Judgments in the midſt of a People, or a Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Prop.</hi> As God doth not delight to execute his Judgments in the midſt of a People, ſo upon honourable Terms to him, and eaſie and profitable to us, he is willing to let fall his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, and with-hold his Judgments from us: See thoſe Places, and conſider them, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 3.12, 13. <hi>Go and proclaim theſe Words toward the North, and ſay, Return thou back ſliding Iſrael, ſaith the Lord, and I will not cauſe mine anger to fall upon yon: For I am Merciful ſaith the Lord, and I will not keep anger for ever. Only acknowledge thine iniquity, that thou haſt tranſgreſſed againſt the Lord thy God, and haſt ſcattered thy ways to the ſtrangers under every green Tree, and ye have not obeyed my Voice, ſaith the Lord.</hi> And <hi>Joel</hi> 2.13. <hi>Micah</hi> 7.18, 19. Beloved, it's from hence abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly manifeſt, that God is willing to be pacified when his Wrath is ſtirr'd up againſt a People or a Nation, if we repent and reform.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Prop.</hi> When God manifeſts himſelf againſt a People or a Nation, if ever Judgments felt be removed, and feared be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, he muſt be complied with in his juſt demands from us: If the Fire of Gods Wrath be extinguiſhed againſt a Nation, the fewel that feeds it muſt be pull'd away: and ſo long as the diſtemper Reigns, proper Phyſick muſt be apply'd, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.11, 12, 13. when Manaſſeh humbled himſelf after he was taken,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98219:8"/>the Lord by intreaty was found of him, to deliver him; and when <hi>Nineveh</hi> faſted and humbled themſelves, the Lord repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him of his anger, and brought not the Deſtruction threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon them; ſo if ever the Lord be intreated for <hi>England,</hi> we muſt be a Reformed People, and turn to the Lord, from whom we have wofully revolted: if ever God hear Prayer, Pardon our National Sins, and heal our wounded and bleeding Kingdom, we muſt ſincerely humble our ſelves, earneſtly pray and unfeignedly turn from the evil of our ways: 2 <hi>Chorn.</hi> 7.14, 15. As all ſorts of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have a Hand in <hi>Englands</hi> threatned Danger, ſo all ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to prevent it by perſonal, ſpeedy Repentance, and thorough Reformation; for is it not the loud Voice of Providence at this day, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.3. <hi>Except ye repent ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh?</hi> So much for the Propoſitions.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) General, is to enquire, what are thoſe Abominations which have, and now do provoke the Lord, by his late Diſpenſations, to declare, as in the Text, <hi>I, even I, am againſt thee, and will execute Judgments in the midſt of thee?</hi> I might anſwer, As all Sin whatſoever is an offence to the Divine Majeſty, ſo like Fuel it adds to the Fire, and helps forwards our now threatned Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery; but more particularly, theſe following, wherever they are found, pull down Wrath and Judgments upon a People or a Nation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is corrupting the true Worſhip of God, and defiling the pure Inſtitutions of Chriſt with the <hi>Inventions of Men;</hi> when thoſe things are made neceſſary, which never came into the Heart of God to ordain, and thoſe things he hath by his Word injoined, are ſlighted and diſregarded: The Diſorder among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> provoked God to viſit them with ſore Trial<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Judgments; and the neglect of Gods Order works all thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out of order, where it is practiſed and allowed: If <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> will offer ſtrange Fire, God will declare their Sin, and ſet up a Monument of his Wrath by the Judgment of <hi>ſtrange Fire</hi> from Heaven to deſtroy them. <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.1, 2. Did not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza</hi> dig his own Grave by going contrary to the command, tho' out of a good In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when he put forth his Hand to ſupport the trembling Ark? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 13.10. Beloved, wherefore did God ſo much let himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was it not for their ſpiritual Whoredoms and Idol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98219:9"/>See <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.14, 15. <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.16. <hi>I will utter my Judgments againſt them, touching all their Wickedneſs, who have forſaken me, and have burnt incenſe unto other gods, and worſhipped the Works of their own Hands:</hi> This way of affronting Gods Authority, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways meets with ſome evident remarks of Gods diſpleaſure: His Heart could not be towards <hi>Iſrael</hi> for it, and had not <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> his choſen ſtood in the gap, he had cut them off in his Wrath. And beloved, if this Sin be found with us, you may know whence Deſtruction comes; nor can we expect it will fare otherwiſe, ſo long as Perſons ſtand more upon Bowing the Head, and bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Knee at the Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and at the ſame time have no regard to be Subject to him in their Hearts and Lives: Corrupting Gods true worſhip provokes Him to declare by his Judgments, <hi>I, even I am againſt you, and will execute Judgment in the midſt of you in the ſight of the Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It's Apoſtacy, backſliding and departing from God, this alſo, ſets God againſt a People or a Nation: When the Inhabitants of a Nation, (as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks of the proudly wicked, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.3, 4.) <hi>He hath left off to be wiſe, and do good, and he ſetteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a way that is not good:</hi> When Perſons by fearful backſliding from God and his ways, which they formerly made Profeſſion of; when the Power of unbelief Reigns to ſuch a Degree, that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons generally depart from God, and the true Doctrine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. And Beloved is not this <hi>Achan</hi> in our Camp? and this <hi>Jonah</hi> in our Ship? yea ſure. Ah! how many are there in <hi>England,</hi> that have forſaken God in their Judgments, by their imbibing Errors for Truth; in their Affections, by loſing their firſt Love; and in their Converſation, by neglecting practical Godlineſs in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies and Civil Employments? Ah, alas! how many are there that were taller, like <hi>Saul,</hi> by the <hi>Head and Shoulders</hi> in the Houſe of God, now have bid adieu, and never come there? how many that were zealous for Gods Worſhip, Publick and Private, now have left off to Hear, to Pray, and inſtruct their Families, Children and Servants? for this wrath is gone out from the Lord; and by his Judgments he ſeems to declare, <hi>I, even I, am againſt thee,</hi> &amp;c. O that theſe Scriptures may be conſider'd by thoſe whoſe Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences tell them, as <hi>Nathan</hi> did <hi>David, Thou art the Man,</hi> Iſa. 1.28, 31. <hi>They that forſake the Lord ſhall be confounded.</hi> 31. <hi>And the ſtrong ſhall be as Tow, and the maker of it as a ſpark; and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98219:9"/>they ſhall both burn together, and none ſhall quench them.</hi> Ezra 8.11. <hi>The hand of the Lord is for good upon all thoſe that fear him, but his Power and his Wrath is againſt all thoſe that forſake him.</hi> Well, you ſee that it is our departing from God, that makes him depart from us; 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.2. <hi>The Lord is with you while ye be with him, and if ye ſeek him he will be found of you; but if ye forſake him, he will forſake you.</hi> O <hi>England!</hi> haſt not thou forſaken thy God? Therefore by his Judgments he now ſaith, <hi>I, even I, am againſt thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Sin which provokes God by his Judgments to declare himſelf againſt a People or a Nation, is Pride; pride, as ſome think, was the Sin that turned the Apoſtate Angels out of Heaven, and hath ſhut them up in Hells Miſery; and it's this Diabolical reigning common Sin of Pride, that hath juſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed the anger of the Lord againſt this Nation. I grant, that the root of Pride is in the Heart, but the Index of it is in the Carriage and Habit of Perſons: And ah, alas! did this Heaven-daring and Nation-deſtroying Sin ever more abound in <hi>England</hi> than now, among all Ranks and Degrees of Perſons? Is it not become a common thing, for Perſons, yea Profeſſors, in effect to quarrel with Gods handy-work, and by their Patching and Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing declare their diſlike of themſelves, becauſe God hath not made them in the Faſhion, tho' ſuch Attires are more to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in <hi>Bedlam,</hi> than permitted in Chriſtian Aſſemblies: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, the high God and proud Perſons, bid defiance one to another. And ſo long as Pride reigns in the Heart, there can be no Peace from God to ſuch a Soul. I grant, Perſons might be diſtinguiſhed one from another by their Habits; but its un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet that any, eſpecially Profeſſours, ſhould exceed the approved bounds of Modeſty; much more that indecent Practice, when the Maid with her Broom is hardly by Habit diſtinguiſhable from Perſons of Honour, and Quality; this ought not to be ſo; and becauſe of this Iniquity, abounding Pride, the Land mourns, and God hath a controverſie with us, as is manifeſt by his executing Judgments in the midſt of us. See theſe Scriptures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.6. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.31, 32. <hi>Behold, I am againſt thee, O thou moſt proud, ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts: For the day is come, and the time that I will viſit thee. And the moſt proud ſhall ſtumble and fall, and none ſhall raiſe him up: and I will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98219:10"/>kindle a Fire in his Cities, and it ſhall devour all round about him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſhameful Prophanation of Gods Holy Sabbath, is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sin, which provokes God by his Judgments to declare himſelf againſt a People or Nation. Beloved, the great God hath conſulted his own Honour, and our good and advantage, and therefore when he might juſtly have requir'd ſix days out of ſeven to himſelf, he hath allowed us ſix for our common Callings, and taken to himſelf but one to be wholly ſpent (excepting Works of Mercy and Neceſſity) in his Publick and Private Worſhip: Butah! how many now plead for a ſinful licentiouſneſs in this day! and make it a light matter to Rob God of his Honour, by ſpending this Holy Day in the ſervice of the Devil, and their own Hearts Luſts: Ah Sirs! is not the Lords day converted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Devils Drudgery? and do not many amongſt us Trade more for Hell than Heaven in it? if we conſider how much of this precious Time is ſpent in Ale-houſes and Taverns, in idle Walks, ſinful Chats, and unneceſſary Viſits; we muſt conclude for this alſo the Land Mourns, and Judgments are executed in the midſt of us, in the ſight of the Nations. See <hi>Neb.</hi> 13.15, 18. O that ſuch a Spirit from the Lord might excite our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Magiſtrates; for verily God is contending for our breach of Sabbaths; and by his late Diſpenſations loudly cries in our Ears, as in <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.27. <hi>If you will not hearken unto me, to hallow the Sabbath-day, and not to bear a burthen, even en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring in at the Gates of Jeruſalem on the Sabbath-day: Then will I kindle a Fire in the Gates thereof, and it ſhall devour the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces of Jeruſalem; and it ſhall not be quenched.</hi> Hear O <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land!</hi> if you will not hallow my Sabbaths, ſaith the Lord, then <hi>I, even I, am againſt thee, and will execute Judgments in the midſt of thee;</hi> as I have done upon my own Day, by Fire and Water, to ſhew my Controverſie with you is very great, and I am againſt you.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Another Sin, which ſets God againſt a People or a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is Stupidity and incorrigibleneſs, under preſent Mercies and Judgments: Beloved, what Nation under the Copes of Heaven, have enjoyed greater Mercies than we have formerly and of late, by a merciful Deliverance from Tyranny and Popery? it was but the other day, when we were laying our Hands upon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98219:10"/>our Loins, and our Faces gather'd paleneſs, and we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd all that is valueable to us upon the Block, and the hands lifted up to give the fatal blow to all, and yet then did their bloody Inventions meet with a happy Prevention, through Gods raiſing up for us a Deliverer; but ah! how have we forget our Vows, and the generality live as tho' they were deliver'd to commit greater Abominations than before: And becauſe Mercies have not melted us to Repentance; therefore Judgments follow one upon the Neck of another, and Gods immediate hand is obviouſly ſtretched out againſt us. Conſider what God ſaid of old to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and is it not his Voice to us now? <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 20. 7, 8. <hi>Then ſaid I unto them, Caſt ye away every man the Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of his Eyes, and defile not your ſelves with the Idols of Egypt: I am the Lord your God. But they rebelled againſt me, and would not hearken unto me: they did not every Man caſt away the Abominations of their Eyes, neither did they forſake the Idols of Egypt: then I ſaid, I will pour out my fury upon them, to accompliſh mine anger againſt them in the midſt of the Land of Egypt.</hi> I think that's applicable to us alſo, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.30. <hi>In vain have I ſmitten your Children, they will receive no Correction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The manifeſt grieving of Gods Holy Spirit, is another great Abomination which provokes God to declare, <hi>I, even I, am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee.</hi> The Holy Spirit of God is griev'd many ways; when the loud Voice of Providences are not regarded, when Miniſters that ſpeak to you with Bowels, in his Name, are ſleigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and their Meſſage not received; when the Spirit comes with Light, and you ſhut your Eyes and will not ſee; when he comes with powerful Convictions, and you ſtifle them; when you are call'd to believe and repent without delay, you will rather hearken to the Devils Verb <hi>mane, delay,</hi> than Gods Adverb <hi>mane,</hi> early, or comply with ſpeed; when Gods Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations on the one hand, and his woes on the other, as by the Prophet, have not their due effect upon us, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13. laſt, <hi>Woe unto thee, O Jeruſalem, wilt thou not be made clean? when ſhall it once be?</hi> (or after, <hi>when yet</hi>) as tho God had ſaid, I have ſtaid long, and ſent time after time, waiting and woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I am now as it Were tired out, if you will comply, well, if not, I muſt, tho with reluctancy, fall on; but O When once ſhall it be! But as it was with them, ſo is it not with us now,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98219:11"/>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9, 10. <hi>In all their Affliction he was afflicted, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of his preſence ſaved them: in his love, and in his pity he redeemed them, and he bare them, and carried them all the days of old. But they rebelled, and vexed his Holy Spirit: therefore he was turned to be their enemy, and he fought againſt them:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, if we in this Nation go on thus to rebell againſt Gods Holy Spirit; if we fight againſt him, and he againſt us; it's no hard matter to tell who will have the worſt; for if he fights, we muſt needs fall; <hi>Who hath harden'd himſelf againſt him and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper'd?</hi> Job 9.4. Thus Beloved, I have ſhewn what are ſome of thoſe crying Sins that provoke God againſt a People or a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I might add many more, as Lying, Swearing, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Oppreſſion, Violence, Ingratitude for National Mercies, non-improvement of ſignal Deliverances from Tyranny and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery to a thorough Reformation, which God expected, as we in Adverſity promis'd the Lord; theſe and the like Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have ſtirr'd up his Wrath againſt us, who ſaith, as in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5.15. <hi>I will go, and return to my place, till they acknowledge their offence, and ſeek my Face: in their Affliction they will ſeek me early.</hi> But I ſhall not enlarge.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) General, What are the black Tokens, and evident Signs of Gods being againſt a People or a Nation? <hi>I, even I, am againſt thee, and will execute Judgments in the midſt of thee, in the ſight of the Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) When Men of Piety, Prudence, and Conduct, are diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited in the midſt of us, and have not that regular zeal for God, Godlineſs, and the Publick Intereſt, as formerly: it was a ſad Omen to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> of what God was about to do with them, when he <hi>took off their Chariot-Wheels, that they drave them hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily,</hi> Exod. 14.24, 25. Men of Piety, Prudence, and Conduct, are as the Chariot-Wheels of the Nation; and if theſe abate their Spirit and Zeal for Godlineſs and the Publick good, our Wheels are off, and we are like to be over-flowed with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Judgments. I remember what God complains of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim,</hi> Hoſea 7.11. <hi>That he was as a ſilly Dove without a Heart;</hi> and is it not applicable to us? What is become of our late Zeal for Godlineſs, amongſt Men of Piety, Prudence, and Conduct, when Popery was coming in by Policy, and Power?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98219:11"/>ſome had a Heart to venture for the publick good in the Face of threatning Dangers; but now when God threatens for want of Reformation, we are ſitting ſtill, and grudge at the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Charges of defenſive War, and are ready to impute our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Miſery to our invaluable Mercy, and ſuffer our cruel Vipers unnaturally to eat out our own Bowels before our Faces: well, its an Argument of Gods being againſt a People, when ſuch Men have loſt their Heart, Spirit and Zeal for Religion, the Publick Good and Safety: This ſpeaks to us, <hi>I, even I, am againſt you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Another Sign of Gods being againſt a People or a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is his permitting Men to be exalted to places of Dignity and Truſt, who are not rightly principl'd for Gods Glory, and the publick's Intereſt: Beloved, I bleſs God day and night hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, for the ſignal favour ſhew'd to theſe Kingdoms, in the happy Acceſſion of the preſent King and Queen to the Throne; (what! two Proteſtants at once!) ſuch a Mercy as hath not been granted to <hi>England</hi> for many Years paſt; and not only ſo, but I bleſs God Publickly and Privately, that by their Royal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, they have ſignified their Pleaſure to have Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Debauchery diſcouraged and trampled under foot; but yet, where the governing Wheels move regularly, if others ſubordinate be defective, the deſirable end will not be obtain'd; if ſome call for and endeavour after a Reformation with hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Succeſs, yet if others will affront Heaven, and deſpiſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by not executing wholſom Laws; what will become of that People where it is ſo? it's no leſs than Irrational to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, where the Leaders of the People be Examples of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs and Debauchery, that there can be any hopeful Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. It was a doleful time, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.13. <hi>When the People turned not to him that ſmiteth them, neither do they ſeek the Lord of Hoſts. But the Leaders of the People cauſed them to err, and they that are load of them are deſtroyed.</hi> When the Caſe of a Land is thus, it might be rightly inferr'd, as the Lord God faith by the Prophet, <hi>I, even I, am againſt thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Another Symptom of Gods being againſt a People or a Nation, is, when neither Mercies nor Judgments are rightly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98219:12"/>Beloved, it's the hearty deſire and endeavour of all whoſe Hearts are right with God, to have all things ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to them, and improved by them to Gods Glory and their good; they full well know, that Mercies not fanctified are real Judgments, and Judgments ſanctified to a right improvement are eventually Mercies; but when neither have their proper end upon a People, it plainly indicates Gods diſpleaſure, and loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeaks that He, even He is againſt them: And now let me tell you, Beloved, we in <hi>England</hi> have had as ſignal Mercies as any Nation under the Heavens; Liberty, Peace, Plenty, and what appertains to this Life and Godlineſs; with a wonderful and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be forgotten Deliverance from apparent eminent dangers; but ah! how evilly have we requited the Lord, and by our obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy and continuance in impenitency and diſobedience, we have cauſed him to turn his Hand againſt us: it was but the other day, and God by his own out-ſtretched Arm wrought Salvation for us, when we were expecting the black Cloud of Tyranny and, Popery to empty it ſelf in ſhowers of Proteſtant Blood, then did the Lord ſend us a Saviour, and we are eſcaped out of the hands of them whoſe avowed Principle it is to murder whom they can't prevail upon to imbibe their damnable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines. And yet ſo amazingly raging is the Frenſie of ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, that we are longing for the Onions and Garlick of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and in a mad fit coveting our former Bondage and Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very: but we hope, as the Blind lead the Blind, ſo both ſhall fall into the Ditch ere it be long: but as we have had ſignal Mercies, ſo we have no leſs remarkable Indications of Gods fore Diſpleaſure; have not Gods four ſore Judgments been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.21.) and do not many now unreaſonably complain of a long and chargeable, tho' juſt, neceſſary and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive War? doth not God himſelf by his immediate Hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Fleet fight againſt us, for Non-Reformation and Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude? yet who conſiders this, or lays it to Heart, or takes right meaſures to have theſe awful Indications of Gods diſpleaſure ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to us, or be improved by us? there's little hope of the Patients health, when no Phyſick hath it's proper end, or kindly operates; ſo it's a ſad Symptom, that the great God is againſt a People, when neither Mercies draw, nor Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments drive to Repentance and Reformation; when it may be truly ſaid of them, as in <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.30. <hi>In vain have I ſmitten your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98219:12"/>Children, they receive no Correction;</hi> or as the Prophet complains, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.11. <hi>Lord, when thy hand is lifted up, they will not ſee: but they ſhall ſee, and be aſhamed.</hi> What can we expect, but that he ſhould ſtill puniſh us ſeven times more, until we do ſee and reform whatſoever is amiſs, under ſuch publick Mercies and National Judgments?</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Another black Token of Gods being againſt a People or a Nation, is Diſcord, and Variance, concerning thoſe things that make for the common good and publick Intereſt: Beloved, Unity and Concord are, under God, the Walls of our Defence; Diſcord and Variance makes us weak, and like a great breach in a cloſe beſieged Caſtle, lays us open to the Rage and Fury of the Enemy: and how ſad is it with that People, where proper Medicines to heal the bleeding wounds of a languiſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, are not apply'd? and how much more ſad, when experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced ones are not made uſe of, where Religion, not Intereſt, would oblige to the greateſt Peril? and how lamentable is it alſo, when the Godly, who are the Props and Pillars of the Kingdom, are divided amongſt themſelves; and ſome ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Tithing Mint, Annis and Cummin, and neglect the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier matters of the Law? It was an old ſtratagem of ſome, and proves often true, (Firſt divide, and then Tyrannize, and do your Pleaſure:) I pray God we in <hi>England</hi> may take heed, this ſeems to be the deſign at this day; and nothing doth more effectually ferve the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Intereſt, and diſſerve ours, than this: Diviſions like the <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe, will let in Ruin inſenſibly upon us: When God would deſtroy <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they made way for it by their Inteſtine Quarrels; and of old, <hi>For the Diviſions of Reuben, there were great Thoughts of Heart,</hi> Judg. 5.15. ſo I wiſh that now for ours alſo, there were great (ſearching of Hearts, and Prudent endeavours to heal and compoſe them made uſe of: for Dogs to tear and devour one another, is natural, but for Sheep to do ſo is ſtrange and unuſual. I remember a Story in <hi>Eſop</hi> to this purpoſe: an aged Father upon a Sick bed, calld his Sons together, and commanded them to bring him a bundle of Twigs, he injoins them to endeavour by pulling to break them, but they could not, then to try again one by one, and they did break them: if we unite, we are like to ſtand; but if we divide, we make our ſelves a prey. O how Happy yet might theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98219:13"/>be, if that once were fulfill'd upon us, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.13. <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im ſhall not envy Judah, and Judah ſhall not vex Ephraim.</hi> I wiſh heartily, that all who profeſs themſelves to be Chriſts ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere followers, would Regard and Practiſe his dying, and New command, to <hi>Love one another, John</hi> 13.34. So call'd, that it might be always minded, and ne'er forgot to be obey'd by us; but if after all that God hath wrought for us, we will obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately perſiſt in ſo great Folly, what can we expect but Ruin? as the Apoſtle hints, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.15. <hi>For if ye bite and devour one another, take heed ye be not conſumed one of another.</hi> For by his Judgments, for this, as well as other Sins, he declares, <hi>I, even I am againſt thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">(5.) Another ſad Symptom of the great Gods being againſt a People or a Nation, is Fruſtration or Diſappointment in common, proper, and ordinary endeavours for the Honour, Safety, and Wealth of a Nation: Beloved, the great God Rules and upholds both Kingdoms and Common-wealths by ſecond Cauſes and ſubordinate Means, ſuch as Merchandizing abroad, Trading at home; and ſometimes by juſt, neceſſary and defenſive Wars with other Nations; but now, when an incenſed God, by his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ruling Providence frowns upon any, or all of theſe, as of late, it ſurely indicates he hath a controverſie with us: was it not the accurſed thing in the Camp, that occaſioned that ſad diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment to <hi>Iſrael</hi> before <hi>Ai?</hi> as <hi>Joſhua</hi> 7.1, 4. And were they not compell'd to reform, according to Gods command, before they could proſper againſt their Enemies? and was it not the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of <hi>Jonah</hi> to Gods Precepts, that cauſed a Storm to ariſe that impeded their Paſſage, until he was thrown over-board? And what may we imagine hath been the occaſion of our late Diſappointments by Sea and Land, but our great Provocations here and there? <hi>For can a Bulruſh grow without Mire,</hi> as in <hi>Job</hi> 8.11? or <hi>will a Lyon roar in the Forreſt, when he hath no Prey,</hi> as in <hi>Amos</hi> 3.4? Neither would God thus blaſt ordinary endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, for our Honour, Safety and Wealth, if we had not by our Sins ſet him againſt us: I muſt confeſs, tho' we have look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for much, and it's come to little; yea, tho' our Trading is Dead in the midſt of us, tho' our Merchants wax Poor, and much of their Wealth is ſwallow'd up in the mercileſs Waves, tho' we have many Widows, Fatherleſs and Orphans, by the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98219:13"/>late deſolating blow from Gods immediate Hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Fleet; yet he that hath done all this, might juſtly have ſwallow'd up all, and have ſpared none to inform us of ſo great a Judgment, commixt with ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſparing Mercy to others, by this repeated Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the incenſed God hath evidently fulfill'd that Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation upon us, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, I will even Rent it with a ſtormy Wind in my Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and there ſhall be an over-flowing ſhower in my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; and great Hail-ſtones in my Fury, to conſume it.</hi> Thus I have given you the Signs of a Black day, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it may be ſaid, as in the Text, <hi>I, even I am againſt thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) General, Is to Evince and Demonſtrate, that of all Judgments, for the great God manifeſtly to declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt a People or a Nation, is the worſt and ſoreſt; and the <hi>Reaſons</hi> are theſe following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Reaſon:</hi> It's ſo, becauſe if God be againſt a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or a Nation, then all he is, in himſelf is againſt that People; as when a Sinner is brought in to Covenant with God, then all in God is his, and for his good, even eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Attribute of God, his Wiſdom, Mercy, Goodneſs, Faithfulneſs, and the like; ſo when God ſets himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a People or a Nation, then every Attribute of God is ſet againſt that People and Nation. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt neceſſarily be the greateſt and worſt of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for God to declare Himſelf againſt a People or a Nation: Beloved, there is infinitely more in the One great God's manifeſting Himſelf againſt us, than if all the World beſides him ſhould do it; ſad was the Caſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when God pronounced by the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.11. <hi>Behold I frame evil againſt you, and deviſe a device a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you.</hi> &amp;c. When the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> ſets his Wiſdom on Work to frame Evil, and deviſe Judgments, it muſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98219:14"/>needs be ſad; for not only one, but all the Attributes of God are againſt that People.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Reaſon:</hi> Of all Judgments, for the great God to manifeſt and declare himſelf againſt a People or a Nation, is the worſt; becauſe then all the Creatures of God are againſt that People: the Lord of Heaven and Earth hath all his Creatures at his beck and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; they do and muſt fulfil whatſoever his Pleaſure is; as a great General once ſaid, If he did but nod with his Head, or ſtamp with his Foot, he could make his Souldiers encounter the greateſt difficulties; ſo if the Lord of Heaven and Earth doth but look out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and ſay as <hi>Jehu</hi> did, to them with proud pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Jezebel,</hi> 2 Kings 9.32. <hi>Who it on my ſide, who?</hi> Then all the Creatures in Heaven and upon Earth, in the Sea alſo, and Winds, ſhall be ready to look out and obey his Commands, and fulfil his Will, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.8. <hi>Fire and Hail, Snow and Vapour, Stormy Wind, fulfilling his Word.</hi> Did not he <hi>cauſe the Stars to fight againſt Siſera?</hi> Judg. 5.20. and did not he ſend an Angel to diſcomfit the Camp of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> who blaſphem'd againſt the Lord? and many more ſuch Inſtances we have, wherein the great God, as well as of late upon the <hi>Straits Fleet,</hi> hath ſhew'd, that it's the worſt of Judgments for God to declare himſelf to be againſt a People, becauſe if he be againſt them, all his Creatures ſhall be againſt them alſo.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is ſo, becauſe if God be againſt a People or a Nation, his Oppoſition renders all other Means ineffectual for our Preſervation, as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.1, 2. <hi>Except the Lord build the Houſe, they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in vain that build it; except the Lord keep the City, the Watchmen watch in vain. 2. It's in vain for you to riſe up early, to ſit up late, to eat the bread of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98219:14"/>Sorrows.</hi> So if the Lord doth not bleſs our Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing, our Trade and Callings, our Forces by Sea and Land, all our Care and Coſt will be in vain. It was a diſmal time with <hi>Saul,</hi> when he cry'd out to him the Witch rais'd, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.15. <hi>I am ſore diſtreſſed and the Philiſtines make War againſt me, and the Lord God hath departed from me.</hi> So if God forſake us in this time of War, ſore Diſtreſs muſt neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: I pray God deliver us from that woful Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation mentioned by the Prophet againſt <hi>Egypt,</hi> Iſa. 19.3. <hi>I will deſtroy the Council of Egypt.</hi> Iſa. 7.7. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God it ſhall not ſtand, neither ſhall it come to paſs.</hi> As with good Advice War is to be made, and in multitude of Counſel is Safety, under God; ſo for God to ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt a People, is the worſt and foreſt of Judgments, becauſe his Oppoſition renders all means for our welfare in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It's the worſt of Judgments, for God to ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt a People or a Nation, becauſe then there is no Safety, but the greateſt Peril; as it is written concerning the Children of the Wicked, <hi>Job</hi> 5.4. <hi>They are far from Safety.</hi> So it may truly be ſaid of that People whom God is againſt, They are far from Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; that is, they are in eminent danger, incompaſs'd with hazards on every ſide, as helpleſs as a naked man is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an incenſed Army, that reſolves to put all to the Sword and ſpare none; when God by Judgments declares as in the Text, <hi>I, even I am againſt thee,</hi> it may truly be ſaid to ſuch, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142.4. <hi>Refuge fails,</hi> and which way ſoever we betake our ſelves, there will be no Exemption from the Judgments of an incenſed God. I remember what the King ſaid to the Woman in the Famine of <hi>Samaria,</hi> to this effect, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.27. <hi>When ſhe cry'd out, Help, O King help! if the Lord do not help thee, whence ſhall I help thee?</hi> intimating, that it was out of his Power, and God only could ſupply her: ſo when the great God declares by his Judgments, <hi>I, even
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98219:15"/>I am againſt thee,</hi> then it is the Language of all created Beings, If God do not help, we cannot; it is natural and common for Perſons in extream danger to ſeek out for help ſome way or other, but when God ſets himſelf againſt a People, their Fingers are rapt off from Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural helps: ſee what God ſpeaks by the Prophet, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.17, 18. <hi>I will bring diſtreſs upon men, that they ſhall walk, like Blind men, becauſe they have ſinned againſt the Lord, and their Blood ſhall, be poured out as Duſt, and their Fleſh as Dung. V.</hi> 18. <hi>Neither their Silver, nor their Gold, ſhall be able to deliver them in the day of the Lords wrath,</hi> &amp;c. You ſee hence, that vain is the help of any Creature, when God is againſt a People; Power, Policy, Wealth, will avail nothing for Safety, when God declares by his Judgment, <hi>I, even I am againſt thee:</hi> Therefore it is the worſt of Judgments.</p>
            <p>Thus you have the Reaſons, which evince the Truth of this awful Doctrine. I now come to make ſome brief Application of the whole.</p>
            <p>The Application of the Doctrine is this.</p>
            <p>If this be ſo, as you hear it is, Of all Judgments, for the great God to manifeſt or declare himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a People, or a Nation, is the worſt and foreſt; then,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From hence, we may plainly ſee the evil and Miſchievous Nature and Conſequence of Sin, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever and by whomſoever it is committed, and continued in without Repentance, and Reformation; it ſets the great God and his Creatures at variance one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>Therefore, ſaith the Lord God, I, even I am againſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98219:15"/>thee;</hi> as in the Text: And wherefore? <hi>Becauſe ye have multiplied more than the Nations that are round about you;</hi> and ye have committed greater Abominations in my ſight, than the very <hi>Heathens;</hi> you have been in your Morals more defective than they, <hi>neither have done according to the Judgments of the Nations that are round about you.</hi> You have been more falſe to Me the true God, than they have been to their falſe gods; you have excell'd them, in Wickedneſs; <hi>Therefore, behold, I, even I am againſt you,</hi> &amp;c. So as you may plainly ſee, what was the cauſe of the great Controverſie God had with them, even their great Abominations; and ſo if we ask, Wherefore is Wrath gone out from the Lord againſt theſe Kingdoms? why doth the Lord contend with us, by the waſting Sword, and impoveriſhing Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? it is becauſe of the Iniquities that are in our Skirts; as <hi>Iſraels</hi> ways and doings procured to them deſtroying Judgments, ſo have ours in <hi>England</hi> pull'd down deſolating Calamities upon us: may it not too truly be ſaid of us in <hi>England,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks in <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> Caralogue of Sins, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>In thee have they ſet light by Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the midſt of thee have they dealt by Oppreſſion with the Stranger, in thee have they vexed the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and the Widow, thou haſt deſpiſed mine holy things, and haſt prophaned my Sabbaths.</hi> And ſcarce one menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, but the like horrid Abominations are to be found in the midſt of us; and when the Lord did for theſe things manifeſt himſelf againſt them, yet that which was worſt of all, is this, <hi>Ver.</hi> 30. <hi>I ſought for a Man among them, that ſhould make up the Hedge, and ſtand in the gap before me for the Land, that I ſhould not deſtroy it; but I found none.</hi> How? was not <hi>Jeremiah</hi> with them, and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> it's concluded was in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi> they would not hearken unto: (but it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that the Lord lookt for one to ſtand up and reform, and amongſt them there was none;)
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98219:16"/>therefore was Indignation poured out upon them: would to God this were not too much our preſent Caſe! Well, if of all Judgments, for the great God to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt himſelf againſt a People or a Nation, be the worſt and foreſt; then ſee what our Sins have done now in the midſt of us, the Lord help us to confider before it be too late.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If this be ſo, then we have, juſt Cauſe to condole the general Supineneſs, Stupidity and Careleſneſs, that Reigns amongſt all forts at this day; altho it's moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that God hath a controverſie with us, Ah, alas! where is the Perſon who hath a becoming Senſe of the Judgments of God in the midſt of us? how few, now God is gone from the Cherub to the Threſhold, <hi>do ſigh, and cry, for all the Abominations done in the midſt of us?</hi> Ezek. 9.4. There's little hope of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients recovery, when he is inſenſible of his Diſeaſe and Danger; ſo there is little hope of better times, while there is ſuch a general Lethargy hath ſeized the Spirits of moſt in this Land: That's our preſent Caſe, which the Prophet complains of, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.11. <hi>Lord, when thy hand is liſted up, they will not ſee; but they ſhall ſee and be aſhamed,</hi> &amp;c. Well, if it be as you hear, we have great Reaſon to lament the general Stupidity that abounds in the midſt of us at this day, when God is executing his Judgments in the midſt of us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If it be ſo, that of all Judgments this is the foreſt, for God to declare himſelf againſt a People or a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then what cauſe have we to ſtand and admire, yea and adore the Infinite Patience of God towards us! That notwithſtanding he is executing Judgments in the midſt of us; yet he hath not made a full End of us, nor
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98219:16"/>overthrown us quite for our Abominations, as he did <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah:</hi> At this day is fulfilled, and made good that Word by the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.8. <hi>My thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your ways my ways, ſaith the Lord.</hi> When Advantage is given, we are for taking it one of another; this is the way of Men too often one with another, but God doth not deal thus with us, after the manner of Men; for in the midſt of Judgments he remembers Mercy: Although God by ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible things in Righteouſneſs anſwers us, yet, we muſt own here is great Mercy commixt with Judgment; for he that hath with his immediate hand upon the Fleet ſwept away ſo many precious Souls, and overturnd ſo much of our Wealth, might with the ſame ſtroak have ſpared none to give us a report of what God hath done againſt us in the ſight of the Nations: Well, as it's leſs than deſerved, ſo it's enough to make us fear and tremble before Him; and ſince he hath manifeſtly a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie with us, we ſhould admire Divine Goodneſs in giving warning, and adore Infinite Patience, that all was not conſumed in Wrath, and that we are yet a People, and not deſtroyed. I come to a Word of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, for I ſhall haſten to conclude, not delighting to inſiſt upon ſuch Tragical Subjects; but the hand of God hath ingaged me in it, beyond my Intention a few days paſt: Therefore,</p>
            <p>By way of <hi>Exhortation:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is this ſo, that of all Judgments, for the great God to declare himſelf againſt a People or a Nation, is the worſt and foreſt that can befall us, then, what ſhall I preſs upon you? ſure I need not exhort you to Credit the Truth of this: It will be eaſily granted, by all that have their Senſes exerciſed to diſcern Divine Truth,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98219:17"/>therefore I addreſs my ſelf to exhort you to theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Place: Be perſwaded and conclude, that the great God hath a Controverſie with theſe ſinful Kingdoms: it's not hard to prove it, God doth by his Frowning Diſpenſations evidently declare it, by what he hath formerly and of late done in the midſt of us, he now as in the Text loudly cries in our Ears: <hi>I, even I am againſt thee.</hi> Beloved, ſo long as we Fancy it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, we ſhall not ſet our ſelves in, good earneſt to the Work, of Reformation, which we are obliged un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and God calls for by his Judgments, and ſaith, to us, as by the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13. laſt, <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, when wilt thou be made clean? when ſhall it once be?</hi> When, when after all that I have done in the midſt of you?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be exhorted to Fear and Tremble before this great God, who now by his frowning Providences, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, he hath a controverſie with us: O that all the Inhabitants of theſe Nations would ſtand in awe of him, who hath made himſelf known to be a Juſt and Holy God, by his Judgments executed upon us! We may evidently ſee that our Abominations have provoked him to Wrath, and if we will not after all this be prevailed upon to make him our dread, what can we expect but that he ſhould proceed to viſit us with greater Calamities than have yet befallen us?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Be exhorted to Reform what in you lies, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before the Lord what you can't obtain from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. I earneſtly intreat every Soul of you, in the Name of the Lord, to begin with his own Heart and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98219:17"/>Houſe; and caſt away, the deteſtable things, which God pleads againſt us for; as good Houſe-wiſes are moſt at home, minding their own concerns; ſo the beſt and moſt upright-hearted Chriſtians are moſt Converſant with their own Hearts, and more concern'd to eaſt the beam out of their own Eyes, than to complain of the Mote in anothers; therefore ſet to the Work of Reformation thy ſelf, and when you have ſtoned the <hi>Achan</hi> in your own Camp, expect to proſper, and not before; and then lay before the Lord the neglect of Reformation by others, go to the Throne of Grace, and weep o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thoſe Sins which are abounding in the midſt of us; and that there is ſo little done to reform, under ſo great Obligations to it, by what National Mercies we yet enjoy upon Trial.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Be exhorted to ſecure your Intereſt in Chriſt, the anointed of God to ſave loſt Sinners; above all things look to this; in times of Diſtreſs wiſe men en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſecure their beſt things, their Jewels, Gold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Beloved in this dark and calamitous day, now God is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending by his Judgments, look to your Souls; above all things, every one get Arkt in Chriſt; for as every Soul out of the Ark periſht in the Deluge, ſo every Soul that dies out of Chriſt muſt periſh Eternally, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. <hi>There is no Condemnation, to them that be in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> ſo there is nothing but Condemnation to them that dye out of him; if the avenger of Blood under the Law laid hold of the Man-ſlayer before he got into the City of Reſuge, there's no relief for him; ſo if you dye out of Christ, you can't eſcape the Wrath of God: O then flee to Chriſt, caſt Anchor within the Vail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, in this ſtormy Seaſon! that if you are not deliverd from Temporal Calamities, you may be freed Him Eternal: ſtudy Chriſt, his Name, Nature and Fulneſs; even that too much eclipſed Name of his,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98219:18"/>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.6. <hi>Toe Lord our Righteouſneſs,</hi> and ſubmit to it, that thou be not found naked of that which only can skreen the Wrath of God off you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.10. <hi>They that know thy Name, will put their truſt in thee.</hi> O that the Tokens of Gods Wrath might in this day move all to prepare an Ark for the ſaving their Souls, I mean to ſecure their Intereſt in Chriſt: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Who of God is made to us, Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Redemption.</hi> In him there is enough for your ſupply, Sinners, therefore haſten by Faith, grapple upon him, who rejects none that come to him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. therefore take him at his Word, he is faithful and can't deny himſelf.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Lift up a Cry, and pour out your Souls to God in Prayer for theſe ſinful and threatned King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; although Wrath is gone out from the Lord, who knows but he will yet be intreated for us, yea if we hear the Rod, and him that hath appointed it; he will remember his former Loving Kindneſſes, for he delights not in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his Creatures, but upon honourable terms to him, and eaſie to us if complied with, he will ſhew Mercy; therefore ſet your ſelves to ſeek the Lord, it may be he hath not ſaid, tho' <hi>Noah, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> pray, he will not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated for us; he formerly hath ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſlow to anger, of great kindneſs and tender Mercy; therefore go home and plead with him, that felt Judgments may be ſanctified, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd and feard Judgments may be prevented, and it may be God will yet dwell in our Land. Thus
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98219:18"/>I have given you my ſhort Meditations upon what the Lord hath done upon our Fleet, by his immediate hand, apparently to all. I pray God, we may ſee, hear, learn, and do no more ſo wickedly, leſt worſe befall us from the Lord than yet hath happen'd.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THe Reader is deſired to amend the <hi>Errata</hi>'s that have eſcaped the Preſs.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
